A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Director of Administrative Services, Roger C. Elliot, Subject Files, Series 3 FA214
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Director of Administrative Services, Roger C. Elliot, Subject Files, Series 3
1904-1974
Rockefeller Archive Center
Flinn, Waldo R.
Elliot, Roger C.
Smith, Edric Brooks
FA214
10.2 Cubic Feet 20 boxes
20 boxes
Biographical / Historical
In 1956 Roger C. Elliot was appointed Assistant Business Manager to work with Waldo Flinn and Douglas Whitaker who had supervisory responsibility for the Office of the Business Manager. In further reorganization Waldo Flinn was named Director of the Budget with Roger C. Elliot as Assistant Director. When Mr. Flinn retired in 1965, and Joseph R. Dilworth, Treasurer, supervised the Office of the Budget and Special Services, Roger Elliot served as Assistant Comptroller.
In 1970/1971 a clear-cut division between financial management of the University and the management of financial properties was re-established. The various positions of Comptrollers were abolished and Roger Elliot became Director of Budgets and Special Services. In 1972 the post of Director of the Budget and Special Services was dropped and budgetary functions were transferred to the Office of Controller.
Roger Elliot as Director of Administrative Services supervised the property management of the University and the administration of faculty benefit plans and all forms of general insurance. Roger Elliot retired as of July 1, 1974 and the post of Director of Administrative Services was discontinued as a separate entity.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 216-3
Scope and Contents
This group of records deals primarily with construction of new facilities or additions and remodeling to existing buildings.
The subject files here described include correspondence and records from the files of Waldo Flinn. Some of the material dates as early as 1904. It consists of records from the Business Manager's Office which were never removed when new appointments to the office were made. The detailed inventory sheets indicate the appropriate dates.
Arrangement
Arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
General
In May 1978 an additional 15 inches (Boxes 18-20) of records dealing with construction were found. Included are records that had been passed along from Edric Smith, Waldo Flinn and finally to Roger C. Elliot. When the Office of Administrative Services was phased out these records were sent to the Archives Office.
Operations management; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Subject Files, 1904-1974; 1956-1974; 3; 10.2 Cubic Feet 20 boxes
  - Animals, 1905-1949 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes early correspondence dealing with stolen dogs. Arrangements to purchase animals abroad and problems of animal care and dwelling facilities. 1913 Henry James report on animal care facilities seen on European trip. Some requests for descriptive material on RIMR animal facilities; some items dealing with lost animals.
  - A-C (various) (Box 1)
    - Arc Welding
    - Archer, Ann
    - Argus Press Clipping Service
    - Armstrong, James, Plumbers
    - Armstrong Cork and Insulation
    - Armstrong Card Products
    - Arndt, M.H. Mfg. Co.
    - Beard, Joseph W.
    - Begg, Jennie
    - Belgium Ambassador (1940 sera request)
    - Bell Telephone
    - Berkeley Scientific Corp.
    - Berry, George Parker
    - Bessey, Otto A.
    - Beukenkamp, John (PVM mice)
    - Beverly, G.H.
    - Business Methods, Report by Trevor Arnett, 1916
    - Committee on Post-War Science. Questionnaire sent by I.I. Rabi
    - Carrel, A. Report on the Hospital at Compiègne, 1916 September-1917 September; 5 pp. mimeograph
    - Carrel, A. Report regarding present and proposed work, 1919 March; 5 pp. mimeograph
  - Budget, 1913-1938; 1939-1961; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Primarily salary matters. Includes some correspondence but consists mainly of comparison tables for various years and with other institutions.
  - Budget charts (Box 1)
    Position distribution; income vs. expenditures.
  - Budgets: unexpended balances, 1956-1957; 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Buildings, 1924-1956 (Box 1)
    Charts and information gathered on size of space assigned to various departments; unit costs; construction costs; trustees' expenditures; depreciation.
  - Contingent Fund a. Potential Contingent Fund, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and approvals, 1953-1955
    - Signed authorizations, 1954-1955
  - Commitments and potential commitments, 1955-1962 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence between Waldo R. Flinn, Charles Petrzelska, Douglas Whitaker, Detlev Bronk and Mabel Bright and heads of departments.
    Arrangement note
    Correspondence arranged by item number on ledger sheets.
    - Potential, 1955-1956
    - Committed, 1955-1956
    - Potential, 1956-1957
    - Potential, 1957-1958
    - Contingent-Potential, 1958-1959; 1959-1960
    - Contingent-Potential, 1960-1961; 1961-1962
  - Construction (Box 3)
    - Correspondence on Hospital construction (Box 3)
      - 1930-1939
      - 1946-1952
    - Primarily correspondence between Edric B. Smith, Walter A. Smith, Henry R. Shepley, Francis V. Bullfinch for Coolidge, Shepley, Bullfinch & Abbott; Fred N. Severud, consulting engineer and Vermilyn-Brown Company (Box 3)
      Includes drawings, suggestions, cost estimates, rising prices. Includes copies of 1946 correspondence between John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Herbert S. Gasser.
    - Specification Books, 1915-1916 (Box 3)
      - Shepley, Rutan & Coolidge, architects Six books, one each
        Alterations to 5th floor and roof of administration bldg.
        Power plant, heating system, refrigeration apparatus
        Connecting corridor and tunnels
        Power House and service building
        Laboratory building
        Animal House.
  - Hospital construction records, 1946-1952 (Box 4)
    - Electrical wiring and fixtures
      Includes drawings and blueprints
    - Electrical work on transformer vault under sidewalk
    - Elevators. Specifications and bids
    - Plumbing. Fred Brutschy Co., contractors
    - Specifications, bids, correspondence on various items arranged in alphabetical order
      Acoustical work
      Air conditioning
      Bathroom tiles, accessories
      Carpenter work
      Concrete floors
      Curtains for cubicle
      Flooring
      Glass and glazing
      Hardware
      Iron work
      Linen or laundry chute
      Lockers
      Marble and stonework
      Metal furring and lathing
      Pantry equipment
      Plaster work
      Refrigerator (Biologicals)
      Reinforced concrete
      Roofing
      Steel doors
      Structural steel
      Tiles
      Weatherstripping.
    - Construction items, 1913-1953
      Includes alterations to nurses residence; bills and payment records; graphs showing rise in construction costs (1913-1951) and changes in hourly labor wages.
  - Plant Pathology building specifications in Princeton, 1931 (Box 5)
  - Plant Pathology building in New York City, 1947-1949 (Box 5)
    Includes correspondence, agreements, cost statements from Coolidge, Shepley, Bullfinch & Abbott; Lord & Burnham; Alvord & Swift; Fred Butschy Co.; Vermilya-Brown Co.
  - Corporation actions (Box 5)
    Arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Consolidation of Princeton and New York City laboratories, 1947/1948 (Box 5)
      Includes background material, considerations, 1947 report from H.S. Gasser on budgetary considerations.
    - Counsel, 1928-1963 (Box 5)
      Primarily correspondence with John E. Lockwood regarding meetings, minutes but also concerning the President's House. Some correspondence with George H.P. Dwight and some with John R.H. Blum.
    - Director, 1932 1952 (Box 5)
      Correspondence and excerpts from meetings dealing with search for second Director of Institute. Also news releases and clippings. 1952 material includes report of Committee on Nomination and Review and some 1958 material on salary.
    - Endowment, 1908-1951 (Box 5)
      Correspondence, excerpts from Minutes and summaries dealing with endowments made by John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Rockefeller Foundation and General Education Board.
    - Endowment. Henry Rutherford Bequest for Cancer work, 1913-1949 (Box 5)
    - Finance Committee, 1937-1955 (Box 5)
      Budgetary plans including estimates of income and planned expenditures presented for consideration of finance committee. Includes excerpts and resolutions from Board of Trustees Minutes, 1925-1957.
    - Treasurer's Office (Edward Robinson; Robert Letort), 1954-1956 (Box 6)
    - Treasurer's Office (Lindsley P. Kimball; William Dietz), 1959-1960 (Box 6)
      Correspondence on budget and income; statements and financial reports.
    - Underwriting Fund against grants, 1956/1957-1961/1962 (Box 6)
  - Deferred Liabilities Reserve (lacks 1959) Primarily correspondence between W.R. Flinn and Bursar including requests for hold over from various laboratories and signed approvals by D.W. Bronk for hold-over amounts, 1956-1962 (Box 6)
  - Descriptive pamphlet Correspondence about various editions (Box 6)
    Includes mailing lists.
    - 1932 1935-1936
    - 1939-1943
  - Dining facilities, 1929-1954 (Box 6)
    Scattered correspondence referring to lunchrooms, costs, personnel, special luncheons.
  - Dining facilities, 1949-1963 (Box 6)
    Welch Hall. Includes costs and supplies, also material on remodeling including blueprints; redecorating; personnel and costs of meals. Photographs of interior and exterior.
  - Dining facilities, 1957-1961 (Box 7)
    Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Hall Details of accommodations for visiting scientists, faculty club and includes some lodging costs. Correspondence on costs and charges.
  - Director's Apartment, 1931-1953 (Box 7)
    Originally called Lavoisier apartments. Correspondence, agreements and details dealing with apartments occupied by Simon Flexner and H.S. Gasser in arrangements with the Institute.
  - Electrocardiogram (Box 7)
    Correspondence with Cambridge Instrument Co., Dr. T.M. Rivers and The Smithsonian Institution on the original Einthoven String Galvanometer. Includes copy of history as written by Alfred E. Conn.
  - Employee workman's compensation (Box 7)
    - Correspondence concerning Edward Patrick, 1919-1920
    - Correspondence about various people, 1918-1964
  - Faculty appointments, 1958-1961 (Box 7)
    Copies of notification letters for appointment as Research Associate; Consultant; Assistant Physician; Guest Investigator.
    Arranged in alphabetical order: A-H; I-Z.
  - International Health Division, 1931-1950 (Box 7)
    Correspondence between W. Flinn and IHD setting monthly charges for space rental.
  - Neighborhood Development, 1925-1951 (Box 7)
  - O (Various); Pavlov, Ivan, 1921-1925 (Box 7)
    Correspondence between S. Flexner; Petrankevitch; W. Sterling; W.B. Cannon; Wickliffe Rose.
  - Retirement; Pension plans (Box 8)
    - Regulations, plans and correspondence, 1913-1939
    - Past service credits to 1939
    - History and considerations for 1939 plan
    - Tables, forms and estimates, 1931-1942
    - Reconsideration of retirement plans, 1931-1948
    - Supplements to retirements prior to 1950
    - Certificate waiving exemption under OASI, 1950 December 29
    - Photocopy from David Rockefeller files
    - Retirement plans amended 1954
  - Scientific annual reports. Changes in form (Box 8)
  - Scientific staff listings (Box 8)
    Listing of staff by year including War Demonstration Hospital Group and various tabular summaries of past service; ratio of scientists to staff; women scientists appointed.
    - 1918-1942/1943
    - 1943/1944-1954
  - Scientific staff, correspondence regarding travel allowances, 1920-1949 (Box 8)
  - Scientific staff, addresses of former RI scientists; Summer addresses of scientific staff, 1932-1939 (Box 8)
  - Scientific staff, 1930-1941 1946 (Box 9)
    Copies of appointment announcements.
  - Sigerist, Henry, 1916-1937 (Box 9)
    1933 correspondence regarding RI photos Squibb, E.R. & Sons 1916-1937 correspondence dealing with some product analyses and purchase of serum horses.
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1912-1942 (Box 9)
    1912-1913 photomicrographs for exhibit Snake venom 1912-1942 includes exchange between S. Flexner and Pasteur Institute.
  - Society of American Bacteriologists meeting announcement, 1952 (Box 9)
  - Students, 1955-1961 (Box 9)
    Correspondence dealing mainly with housing matters but including some letters of notification.
    Bates, Harold
    Bonneville, Mary
    Cohn, Robert
    Corner, Michael
    Fulton, Chandler
    Goldberg, Irving
    Hopkins, Johns Wilson
    Lacks, Sanford A.
    Lester, Hugh
    Osterhout, Suydam
    Paasche, Eystein
    Peachy, Lee D.
    Petropulos, Stephen
    Rose, John
    Simon, Harold
    Tormey, John McDivit.
  - Special events, 1917-1935
    Material on receptions, parties, teas, symposia and lectures where RIMR has been host and includes guest lists, invitations, menus, expenses and programs.
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - Reception given by Dr. and Mrs. Flexner, Cole T. Smith and Henry James, 1917 January 12 (Box 9)
    - Reception in honor of 20th anniversary given by Mrs. Flexner for Scientific Directors, 1922 January 20 (Box 9)
      Copy of John D. Rockefeller greetings read by John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
    - Plans for Dinner Dance to be given by Dr. and Mrs. Flexner. Cancelled because of S. Flexner illness, 1929 May 4 (Box 9)
    - Plans for American Laboratory Theatre performance arranged by Dr. and Mrs. Flexner. Postponed, 1930 May 2 (Box 9)
    - Supper given by Dr. and Mrs. Flexner to meet Board of Scientific Directors, 1931 January 16 (Box 9)
    - Dr. and Mrs. S. Flexner At Home, 1932 April 8 (Box 9)
    - Dinner Dance given by Dr. and Mrs. Flexner, 1932 December 3 (Box 9)
    - Reception by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for Dr. S. Flexner, 1935 October 7 (Box 9)
      Information incomplete - event may have been cancelled.
    - Physiological Congress (13th), 1929 August 28 (Box 9)
      Includes correspondence between Graham Lusk, Simon Flexner, W.J.V. Osterhout (some holograph) dealing with arrangements, programs and menus. Includes a number of photographs of tables arranged outdoors.
    - Karl Sudhoff lecture, 1929 October 22 (Box 9)
    - Charles Singer lecture, 1930 May 13 (Box 9)
    - Henry E. Sigerest Lecture, 1931 November 11 (Box 9)
    - William H. Welch sound film made in 1932 but exhibited in 1933 and again in 1942 February 6, 1933 January 18 (Box 10)
      Conditions Governing Access
      RAC is unable to provide access to the original film. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
      Separated Materials
      Original Film was seperated to RAC Film Vault, May 1983.
      Consists of 1932-1943 correspondence with W.G. MacCallum and Alan M. Chesney regarding copies and ownership of film. Includes transcript of address "Reminiscences of the Early Days of the Medical Scool".
    - Reception to meet H.S. Gasser, 1935 November 26 (Box 10)
    - Luncheons for Staff, Directors, Board usually including a speaker, 1919-1953 (Box 10)
      Includes invitations, seating arrangements and menus.
    - Professor Einthoven of Leyden, 1924 November 26 (Box 10)
    - In honor of P.A.T. Levene, 1930 January 13 (Box 10)
    - American Chemical Society Medicinal and Biological sections, 1935 April 26 (Box 10)
    - Pasteur Vallery-Radot, 1935 May 10 (Box 10)
      Includes resume of lecture "The Logical Sequence of Pasteur's Work".
    - Reception for 3rd International Congress of Microbiology. Dr. Rivers President, 1939 September 4 (Box 10)
      Also demonstrations in Institute laboratories. Official medal of 1939 Congress is in memory of Theobald Smith "Father of American Bacteriology". Two plaques of medal presented to Institute one for Library and one for Princeton laboratories.
    - American Chemical Society smoker, 1947 September 18 1951 September 7 (Box 10)
      1947 by Division of Biological Chemistry; 1951 12th International Congress of Pure and Applied Chemistry.
    - Correspondence dealing with reserving rooms for various groups meeting at the Institute including seminars, guest lectures, luncheon meetings, "Growth" discussion group, 1948-1958 (Box 10)
      Includes 1956, 1957, 1958 schedule of lectures for graduate fellows.
    - Testimonial dinner for Dr. Gasser given at the University Club. Invitations sent by David Rockefeller, 1953 June 30 (Box 10)
    - Reception for D.W. Bronk, 1954 January 22 (Box 10)
      Includes details of preparations, guest lists and some handwritten regrets.
    - 50th anniversary celebration of Institute's first laboratory building, 1954 October 15 (Box 10)
      Reception, naming of old buildings, ground breaking for new buildings, addresses. Includes some handwritten notes of acceptance or regret Addresses are: Richard Edwin Shope. Theobald Smith; Thomas McElrath Debevoise. John Davison Rockefeller; Eugene Lindsay Opie. The First Laboratory of the Institute; Alan Mason Chesney. William Henry Welch; Peyton Rous. Simon Flexner.
    - Faculty/Student teas, 1954-1961 (Box 10)
      1955 tour of Institute for new members, visiting investigators and students.
    - Society of American Bacteriologists, 1955 May 9 (Box 10)
      Correspondence much of which is signed by Merrill Chase; sample program, ticket. Includes costs, menu, flower arrangements.
    - Farewell party for Dr. Rivers and E.B. Smith on their retirement, 1955 October 20 (Box 11)
    - Tea for Dr. Rivers and Dr. Gasser, 1958 January 17 (Box 11)
    - Christmas parties: 1955, 1956, 1957, 1958, 1955-1962 (Box 11)
      Dr. Bronk's parties for Institute; 1959-1962. Childrens' Christmas parties; 1959-1960. Includes students' Christmas Ball.
    - Events assorted by date held at Rockefeller Institute but not necessarily sponsored by RI, 1955-1962 (Box 11)
      - National Citizens Committee for WHO, 1955 June 3
      - Veterans Administration (artificial limbs), 1955
      - Eastern Surgical Society, 1958
      - Artificial pacemakers, 1958
      - Health Research Inaugural, 1958
      - European Chemists and Pharmacists, 1958
      - Childrens' Asthma Research Institute, 1958
      - Institute of Radio Engineers, 1958
      - Conference on Diagnostic Data Processing, 1959
      - International Society of Aviation Workers, 1959
      - Atoms for Peace Awards, 1959
      - American Society of European Chemists, 1959
      - Johns Hopkins Alumni Association, 1959 1960 1961 1963
      - American Medical Writers Association, 1959
      - Chemical Instrumentation Conference, 1959
      - American Women's Association, 1960
      - American Society of Biological Chemists, 1960
      - Health Research Council, 1962
    - Medical Electronics, 1955-1963 (Box 11)
      Various meetings, center temporarily at RI established to improve contact between electronic specialists and medical and biological scientists. Vladimir Zworykin at RI. leader.
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1957 November 18-20 (Box 11)
    - Official Paul Weiss Press Conference (State Department on Brussels Fair), 1958 (Box 11)
    - Symposium on Molecular Biology, 1958 September 25-30 (Box 11)
      2 folders of correspondence dealing with arrangements and correspondence on travel with participants.
    - David Rockefeller party (only expense list), 1958 December 19 (Box 11)
    - Dr. Smillie retirement, 1958 September 28 (Box 11)
    - Fred Capalino retirement, 1959 September 30 (Box 11)
    - Convocation expenses, 1959 (Box 11)
    - Symposium of Basic Research sponsored by Rockefeller Foundation, AAAS, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, 1959 May 14-16 (Box 11)
    - Assorted seminars, meetings lectures and luncheons, 1959-1964 (Box 12)
      Correspondence deals with arrangements for space. Events not necessarily sponsored by RI.
    - CBS Great Challenge broadcast from Caspary Auditorium, 1960 1961 1963 (Box 12)
  - Tariff, Changes in tariff for imported scientific material, 1920-1922 (Box 12)
  - Telegrams, 1942 1949 (Box 12)
  - Telephone, 1929-1935 (Box 12)
    Installation plans; change to dial Survey.
  - T (miscellaneous) (Box 12)
    - Ter Louw, Adrian. Application, correspondence, transcript, holograph from R. Wyckoff, 1930-1933
    - Thomas, Andrew J., architect, 1924-1931
      Material about housing construction including pages from Architectural Record. Four letters (April 1931) about electrical outlets in Director's apartment.
    - Thompson, Correspondence and final item on retirement, 1917 March-1938; 21 + 1 items
    - Topka, Frank, employee benefits at illness and death, 1929-1935
  - Tennis Courts: type of construction; scheduling of courts, 1916-1932, 1933-1941 (Box 12)
  - Time clock, 1919-1957 (Box 12)
    Regulations governing work hours, time clock registration and change from use of time clock.
  - Tractor, 1947-1951 (Box 12)
    Used for snow removal at Princeton laboratories. Correspondence with Cater and Jones, Insurance, when Princeton labs closed.
  - Travel, 1955-1961 (Box 12)
    Contract with TWA.
  - Tryparsamide, 1925 (Box 12)
    Listing of countries with dates of trademark registration and expiration. October 1925 report by Wade Brown and Louise Pearce. Photocopy of letter and news article regarding use of drug by Mrs. Georgia Wood.
  - Tuberculosis, 1913-1953 (Box 12)
    Assorted news clippings and correspondence.
  - Unemployment, 1932-1934 (Box 12)
    Emergency Committee formed to aid unemployed. Includes typescript letter signed by Nicholas Murray Butler.
  - Unions, 1933 (Box 12)
    Development of union agitation with acceptance of National Recovery Act. Reexamination of RIMR working hours.
  - United Mine Workers, 1956; USO 1946; United States Pharmacopoeial Convention (Box 12)
  - United States (Box 13)
    - Agriculture Department, 1915-1949
    - Army Department, 1942-1944
    - Commerce Department, 1922-1951
      Includes 1949 correspondence on the importing of monkeys.
    - Immigration Bureau of Labor Department, 1917-1949
      Includes correspondence on individuals and also explanations of RI as an educational institution in respect to foreign students.
    - Labor Department Women's Bureau, 1947
      Includes 1947 correspondence regarding publication "The Outlook for Women in Chemistry".
    - National Labor Board/Manpower Commission, 1943-1945
    - Post Office
      Regulations for mailing specimens of infectious materials.
    - Public health Service, 1956-1965
      Policies, practices and information on NIH grants.
    - Senate. Five items dealing with Hubert Humphrey sub-committee studying the role of private organizations in international medical research and service fields, 1958
    - State Department, 1915-1936
      Early correspondence deals with necessary clearances for shipments from Germany of glassware during WW I; later with representation at international meetings.
    - Surgeon General, 1917-1924 1927 1945
      Primarily related to War Demonstration Hospital and to anti-meningitis serum.
    - Treasury Department, 1915-1956
      Deals with narcotics regulations; hospital census, sale of treasury bonds; tax exempt status.
    - War Department, 1931-1952
      Miscellaneous materials including correspondence on the blasting and dredging operations in the East River. Includes request for free copies of RIMR journals during 1934 budgetary crisis.
  - Uy, Milagras E. (Mrs. Jacoby) Dietition in the U.S. on a visitor's visa. Attempt to extend stay (Box 13)